Introduction
Humanity, created by God in all its grandeur, is today facing a pivotal choice:
either to construct a new Tower of Babel or to build the city in which God and
humanity dwell together. Each generation inherits the task of shaping its own era,
Founded on Christ, the living stone, we experience the powerful and mysterious
action of the Holy Spirit, and we believe that every authentic human effort to
cooperate with him for the good will be blessed by our heavenly Father, in whom we
In this spirit, Pope Leo XIII published his Encyclical Rerum Novarum in 1891, the
135th anniversary of which we celebrate with deep gratitude this year. With that
document, my beloved predecessor gave impetus to the reflection on society, the
The res novae of our time
Meditation on the occasion of the Prayer Vigil and Rosary for Peace (11 October
2025): L’Osservatore Romano, 13 October 2025, 2. 301. 223 82 Given in Rome, at Saint
Peter’s, on 15 May, in the year 2026, the second of my Pontificate. LEO PP. XIV
It now falls to us to face the challenges of our time with clarity of thought and
responsibility. It is necessary to establish adequate regulatory tools capable of
upholding justice and curbing the distorting effects of technological power.
For this reason it is necessary to begin a shared discernment process for
identifying the spiritual and cultural roots of ongoing transformations. If we focus
only on contingencies, we risk letting the succession of emergencies dictate the
Two biblical images
In order to answer these questions and discern how to navigate responsibly the era
of AI, I would like to bring to mind two scenes from the Bible: the construction of
the Tower of Babel (cf. Gen 11:1-9) and the rebuilding of the walls of Jerusalem
The Book of Nehemiah, in turn, opens at a time of great vulnerability in the history
of ancient Israel. After the Babylonian exile, a portion of the people returned to
Jerusalem, but the city was still in ruins, the walls collapsed and the gates burned
In light of these two images, the Holy Spirit challenges us today regarding our
relationship with technology and the ongoing digital revolution. Scientific
discoveries are talents entrusted to humanity so that they may bear fruit (cf. Mt
We must, then, avoid the “Babel syndrome,” namely the idolatry of profit that
sacrifices the weak, a uniformity that neutralizes differences, and the pretense
that a single language — even a digital one — can translate everything, including
Building for the common good
Building a city founded on the common good implies, first and foremost, building on
a firm relationship with God. It means recognizing that the truth of his love calls
us to life “in all its fullness” (Jn 10:10) and communion with him. Like Saint
Secondly, building for the common good means accepting the limits and weakness of
humanity without considering them an error to be corrected. Today, the human desire
for fullness of life is at risk of being misled by deceitful goals, such as the
Thirdly, building a world in which everyone can flourish requires shared
responsibility and courage. No one can single-handedly bear the weight of the
challenges the world is facing, just as no one is so weak that they cannot play
Finally, building for the common good requires an evangelical language. We must
avoid humiliating or antagonistic words, opting rather for a clarity that sheds
light and a frankness that unlocks new possibilities. We cannot condone naïve
Remaining human
139-141. 61 limited geopolitical relevance, are currently subjected to a new mindset
of extraction: that of health data, epidemiological profiles, genetic maps and
demographic information. These have become the new “rare earths” of power: vital
I address this heartfelt appeal to all the Catholic faithful, to all Christians and
to all men and women of goodwill. Let us not be afraid to get our hands dirty on the
“construction site” of our time. Like Nehemiah, let us pray, plan wisely and work
A Dynamic Approach Faithful to the Gospel
13 to be challenged by the signs of the times, and draws nourishment from the
contributions of science, culture and human experience. Therefore, when the dignity
of our brothers and sisters is violated, when politics fails to address the
This overview, however, would not be very comprehensible if, before reflecting on
the contribution of individual popes and their most relevant documents, we do not
first clarify some fundamental principles concerning the way in which the Church
A Church journeying through human history
The Church is present in the world as a sign of unity for the entire human family.
She recognizes today’s questions and challenges as the current setting in which to
carry out her particular vocation of listening, dialogue and service, and of being
The Church’s vocation and duty to accompany humanity in the specifics of history
leads her to recognize that earthly realities possess their own proper character and
order. The Second Vatican Council expressed this principle with particular precision
Recognizing that God upholds the freedom of men and women in the unfolding of
history, the Second Vatican Council affirmed the distinction between the ecclesial
community and the political community, emphasizing that each must operate with full
Starting from this twofold acknowledgment — the autonomy of earthly realities and
the distinction between ecclesiastical and political spheres of competence — allows
for a clearer understanding of the direction that the Second Vatican Council set for
The wisdom of the word of God in dialogue with the human sciences
The Church regards all who sincerely seek “truth, goodness and beauty” as companions
on the journey, and considers them as “precious allies” in defending the dignity of
every person and in caring for creation. Adopting the pastoral approach of the
Nourished by this fruitful dialogue between the Gospel and human knowledge, the
Church has progressively developed her Social Doctrine, cultivating in history a
wise patrimony marked by theological and anthropological coherence rooted in the
Social Doctrine as a shared discernment
Understanding that the truth is a gift to be shared, not a possession to be
monopolized, frees the Church from the temptation of seeking forms of presence based
on power. In order to rediscover the evangelical approach of a gentle proclamation
This attitude of openness to truth, which is at the same time both one and diverse,
profoundly expresses the catholicity of the Church, for she embraces the entire
human family yet is also immersed in the concrete situations of peoples and
In light of what has been said so far, the Church’s Social Doctrine can be seen more
authentically. It is not a handbook of principles and norms to be applied, but a
process of shared discernment. It is born from the encounter between the eternal
The development of Social Doctrine from Leo XIII to the present
Having outlined the way in which the Church is present in history and engages in
dialogue with the world, I would now like to consider the development of Social
Doctrine in the Magisterium, which has responded to the major social transformations
The first stages of the Church’s Social Doctrine
What we now call the “Social Doctrine of the Church” is not a spontaneous product of
the modern age. Instead, it is the fruit of receiving and structuring a long
tradition of ecclesial reflection on life in society, rooted in Sacred Scripture,
Leo XIII’s Encyclical Rerum Novarum constitutes a milestone in the development of
the Church’s social teaching. The document places the dignity of work and of workers
at the forefront of its reflection; affirms the right to a fair wage for oneself and
Pius XI’s Encyclical Quadragesima Anno was published in 1931 on the fortieth
anniversary of Rerum Novarum at the height of a major global economic crisis,
marking a further step in the Church’s social teaching. Rather than limiting itself
In the tragic context of the Second World War, and the years of reconstruction that
followed, the teachings of Pius XII made a significant contribution to the
development of Social Doctrine. This is particularly true of his Christmas radio
The years of the Second Vatican Council
A new phase in the Church’s social teaching began with Saint John XXIII, who placed
a greater emphasis on the global dimension of social issues and the language of
rights. In Mater et Magistra, he presented the Christian faith as a light capable of
The Second Vatican Council marked a turning point in the Church’s understanding of
herself in the contemporary world. In the Pastoral Constitution Gaudium et Spes, the
Council presented the image of a Church that is close to humanity, engaged with the
During the Pontificate of Saint Paul VI, an understanding of peace emerged that was
not reduced to the mere absence of war, but took shape within the scope of integral
human development. In Populorum Progressio, he described development as a transition
In Octogesima Adveniens, written on the occasion of the eightieth anniversary of
Rerum Novarum, Paul VI applied this perspective to postindustrial society, marked by
urbanization, new forms of poverty and rapid cultural changes that called into
The recent Magisterium
The rich social teaching of Saint John Paul II lies at the crossroads of the crisis
of the great ideological systems of the twentieth century and the onset of economic
globalization. His Encyclical Laborem Exercens, written ninety years after the
648. Cf. SECOND VATICAN ECUMENICAL COUNCIL, Pastoral Constitution Gaudium et Spes,
26: AAS 58 (1966), 1046-1047. 58 23 or her choices and actions. At other times, we
think of social dignity, which refers to a person’s living conditions and the
On the centenary of Rerum Novarum, the Encyclical Centesimus Annus offered a
reflection on the collapse of the Soviet system and the rise of democracy and the
market economy. Saint John Paul II reiterated Pius XII’s message that the Church
In his social Encyclical Caritas in Veritate, Pope Benedict XVI sought to reassess
and expand the concept of development presented in Populorum Progressio,
interpreting it in light of globalization. He noted that such development should
Benedict XVI placed charity at the center of his analysis, stating that it “is at
the heart of the Church’s Social Doctrine,” provided that it is always united with
truth. He also noted with concern that there is a tendency to dismiss moral
Pope Francis’ social teaching develops along the lines of Gaudium et Spes, which
invites us to view history through the lens of human hopes and vulnerabilities, and
to bring them into dialogue with the Gospel. This approach emerges with particular
In Laudato Si’, Francis provided the first significant systematic treatment of the
environmental crisis in a social Encyclical, demonstrating that it is not an
isolated issue, but rather the ecological aspect of the contemporary socio-economic
Faced with the breakdown of the social fabric, a “world war being fought piecemeal,”
individualistic globalization and the impact of the pandemic on community ties,
Francis, in Fratelli Tutti, sought to revive the dream of a humanity that opts for
Interpreting history in the light of faith
Considering this historical overview, it is clear that the Church’s Social Doctrine
is not the result of a project devised at a desk, but rather the product of a
patient process in which each pontiff — together with the Second Vatican Council —
Foundations and Principles of the Social Doctrine of the Church
The Social Doctrine of the Church is a living reality, in dialogue with history,
cultures and sciences. At the same time, it enshrines a core set of unchanging
truths. For this reason, it can be considered a form of wisdom that is capable of
In offering these reflections, my hope is, first and foremost, to help the lay
faithful and people of goodwill rediscover their duty of implementing the
abovementioned principles in their daily lives, family relationships, work and
The foundations of Social Doctrine
The human person: image of the Triune God
The Church’s Social Doctrine brings us to the very heart of our faith: the mystery
of the living God, revealed in Jesus Christ, who, as a communion of Persons —
Father, Son and Holy Spirit — is love itself in relationship, expressed in the
If the mystery of God as Love is the source of Social Doctrine, we see its most
concrete expression in the face of Jesus Christ, the Incarnate Word. By becoming
man, the Son of God enters our history and takes on human flesh, bringing with him
At the heart of the Christian understanding of the human person lies the great
biblical affirmation that men and women are created in the image and likeness (cf.
Gen 1:26-27) of the Triune God. Created for relationship, every human person is
The equal dignity of all human beings
Saint John Paul II stated that, “this heightened sense of the dignity of the human
person and of his or her uniqueness, and of the respect due to the journey of
conscience, certainly represents one of the positive achievements of modern
When we speak of dignity, we do not always use the word in the same way. Sometimes
we refer to moral dignity, namely the way in which a person directs his
36 Guardini remain relevant: “Contemporary man has not been trained to use power
well.”
The supreme value of human rights
The Church gratefully acknowledges that “the movement toward the identification and
proclamation of human rights is one of the most significant attempts to respond
effectively to the inescapable demands of human dignity.” In this regard, Saint John
Human rights are inviolable, since they are “inherent in the human person and in
human dignity.” Consequently, they are universal and inalienable. Precisely because
they are grounded in the common dignity of every man and woman, they have practical
Looking at our own time, we cannot ignore the fact that the protection of human
rights has been exposed to two particularly serious dangers. The first is that these
rights are declared in a purely formal sense, while technological progress continues
Along with a greater awareness of the value of every human person and their rights,
recognition of minority rights has also grown. Yet, there is still a long way to go
to ensure that the rights of a great many, namely women, are equally and genuinely
It is individuals that matter, each and every person, together with their families.
Social movements, communal ideologies and grand political proclamations in favor of
a population are worthless unless they lead to the flourishing of persons — men and
The principles of Social Doctrine
The principle of the common good
Recognizing that every man and woman possesses an inalienable dignity, together with
rights that no human power can betray or nullify, requires us to shape the way we
live together, including our economic and political choices, and the makeup of our
The Second Vatican Council affirmed that the common good consists in “the sum total
of social conditions which allow people, either as groups or as individuals, to
reach their fulfillment more fully and more easily.” This definition provides us
In this sense, we can say that the whole is “greater than the sum of its parts” and
that, for this very reason, “the mere sum of individual interests is not capable of
generating a better world for the whole human family.” Indeed, it is an illusion to
It is the pursuit of the common good that gives life to a people, understood not as
a mere collection of individuals, but as a living reality in which people learn to
recognize that they themselves are interconnected and jointly responsible for the
It is the State’s responsibility to ensure cohesion, unity and the proper
organization of civil society, so that the common good can be pursued with
everyone’s contribution. In practical terms, this means that public authorities have
This also applies to international politics. As the divide between nations widens, a
mentality of confrontation and aggression begins to take hold, and the difficult
path toward a more united and fraternal world suffers new and painful setbacks. In
The principle of the universal destination of goods
“Among the numerous implications of the common good, immediate significance is taken
on by the principle of the universal destination of goods.” First of all, this
principle reminds us that the earth’s goods — soil, water, air and natural resources
Certainly there is a right to private property, which has its own specific meaning
and purpose, yet it is always subordinate to the universal destination of goods.
According to John Paul II, this subordination is the golden rule of social conduct
Today, among the goods that are universally intended for everyone, we must also
include new forms of property, such as patents, algorithms, digital platforms,
technological infrastructure and data. In a context where the wealth of nations
The principle of subsidiarity
The principle of subsidiarity stems from the very same understanding of the human
person that has guided our reflection on dignity and the common good. If every woman
and man is called to take ownership of his or her own life and to contribute to the
Starting with Leo XIII and the beginnings of modern social teaching, the Church has
insisted that neither the individual nor the family should be subsumed by the State,
but should be allowed to act freely, as far as possible, without harming the common
This principle encourages us to move beyond any form of paternalistic or
welfare-based management of societal life, but instead to promote a culture of
shared responsibility in a State that values citizens’ initiative, and a civil
The principle of subsidiarity applies especially in the context of the digital
revolution. Here, the highest level is not the State, but rather major economic and
technological actors that exercise de facto power over the conditions of everyday
In this context, States and transnational institutions are called to ensure fair
rules and effective safeguards, so that local communities, intermediary
organizations, schools, universities, religious institutions and associations have a
The principle of solidarity
Having considered the common good and subsidiarity, I would like to reflect on the
principle of solidarity. This emerges from a vision of the human person generated by
faith, namely that every human being is created in the image of God and is part of a
In many areas, we are already experiencing a kind of “de facto solidarity,” for our
lives are intertwined; digital networks connect people and communities across the
world in real time, and global economies and communications mean that events in one
The Church’s social teaching emphasizes that solidarity is both a principle and a
virtue. As a principle, it expresses the objective order of relationships among
individuals, groups and peoples, pointing to an awareness of interdependence whereby
In a world marked by increasingly close connections between people, communities and
nations, solidarity also takes on a global dimension. Benedict XVI strongly
emphasized the link between development, justice and responsibility toward future
The principle of social justice
For the Christian community, social justice is a concrete way of following Jesus and
remaining faithful to the Gospel. In the New Testament, Jesus proclaims the “good
news to the poor” (Lk 4:18) and identifies himself with the lowly, the sick, the
The recent Magisterium has insisted that social justice begins with the least among
us. Saint John Paul II spoke of a preferential option for the poor106 that must
guide both personal and societal choices, while Pope Francis denounced a “‘throw
The idea of “social justice” helps us recognize that injustices do not arise solely
from the wrong choices of individuals, but also from structures, mechanisms and
economic and cultural systems that produce inequality almost automatically. Saint
In this day and age, social justice must also grapple with the environment shaped by
digital technologies. The spread of global networks, platforms and artificial
intelligence systems is changing the way we obtain information, communicate and
A litmus test for social justice today is the treatment of migrants, refugees and
those forced to move due to poverty, violence, climate change and environmental
disasters. The way a society treats them reveals whether its sense of justice is
Integral human development
In his Encyclical Populorum Progressio, Paul VI affirmed that development is
authentic only if it is “integral,” meaning that it can “foster the development of
each man and of the whole man.” 110 In the decades that followed, the Social
For individuals as well as for nations, development is both a duty and a right.
Minimum conditions are required for enabling every person and people to flourish in
accord with their dignity, without being kept in a state of dependence or excluded
Today, the concept of integral human development is a benchmark for the evaluation
of integral ecology, which has become an indispensable dimension of the Church’s
Social Doctrine. Indeed, the quality of development is measured by the ability to
Seen in this light, integral human development is the framework through which we can
interpret the changes of our time, including those brought about by the digital
revolution. Technological innovations, including artificial intelligence, are not
An examen for the Church
In conclusion, I would like to touch on a point that is particularly close to my
heart. Social Doctrine is not merely a message addressed to society; it is also an
examination of conscience for the Church — a home and school of communion that is
With this in mind, subsidiarity becomes the guiding principle for governance and
pastoral life. It involves recognizing and supporting the faithful and intermediary
ecclesial organizations as they carry out their responsibilities, valuing charisms
For the Christian community, solidarity finds its source in the mystery of Christ
and is nourished by the Eucharist. Solidarity emerges from communion in faith and
the Sacraments: Baptism and Confirmation unite us in Christ, so that we may become
Living out justice in the Church means purifying ecclesial relationships and
structures from distortions that give rise to inequality, lack of transparency and
Final Document of the Second Session of the XVI Ordinary General Assembly of the
Technology and Dominance — The Grandeur of Humanity in Light of the Promises of AI
Having recalled the principles that shine a light on Social Doctrine, I would now
like to focus on certain challenges that profoundly shape our way of living today.
The biblical image accompanying these reflections is that of a building project. On
I am convinced that the concrete way of living out social relationships in the light
of the Gospel is not established once and for all, but remains a task entrusted,
from generation to generation, to the Christian community. Under the guidance of the
The technocratic paradigm and digital power
In his Encyclical Laudato Si’, Pope Francis denounced the growing dominance of a
technocratic paradigm119 in our globalized world: the tendency to let the logic of
efficiency, control and profit alone shape personal, social and economic decisions.
This paradigm has spread rapidly in recent years, fueled in part by the expansion of
artificial intelligence, cognitive science, nanotechnology, robotics and
biotechnology. In themselves, these innovations can greatly serve integral human
The danger of humanity becoming a victim of its own achievements was already clearly
recognized by Saint Paul VI, who warned that “the most extraordinary scientific
progress, the most astounding technical feats and the most amazing economic growth,
Here, we must recognize another crucial aspect, which I have noted earlier. In many
cases within the digital context, control over platforms, infrastructure, data and
computing power does not rest with States, but with major economic and technological
Faced with this concentration of power in the digital world, the criteria for
judgment and discernment in this new situation are the noble principles of Social
Doctrine: the inalienable dignity of the human person, the common good, the
Artificial intelligence
It is not my intention here to offer a comprehensive treatment of artificial
intelligence, nor to give an overview of the extensive relevant literature, since
authoritative contributions already exist, including within the ecclesial
It is appropriate to preface this discussion with two considerations. First, any
statement regarding AI risks becoming quickly outdated, given the remarkable pace at
which these systems are developing. Second, all of us, including those who design
It is not possible to provide a single, comprehensive definition of AI. What can be
stated, however, is that we must avoid the misconception of equating this type of
“intelligence” with that of human beings. These systems merely imitate certain
A valuable tool that requires vigilance
In light of what has been said, we can better understand why AI can be a valuable
tool and, at the same time, why it calls for a measured and vigilant approach. In
recent years, its private use has expanded significantly, prompting growing
Broadening our perspective to the use of AI in society, we see that it is now
embedded in decision-making processes across many sectors and at multiple levels: in
communication, management and control. The gains in efficiency and the potential to
Responsibility, transparency and the governance of AI
The use of AI is never a purely technical matter: when it enters processes that
affect people’s lives, it touches on rights, opportunities, status and freedom.
Important and sensitive decisions — concerning employment, credit, access to public
Indeed, entrusting an algorithm in practice with the power to select who is worthy
or not, without anyone bearing responsibility for that judgment, is to hand over the
task of redefining the boundaries of human possibilities. In this process, political
From this follows a simple but compelling consequence: we cannot consider AI to be
morally neutral. In reality, every technical tool embodies choices and priorities
through what it measures, ignores and optimizes, and how it classifies people and
For AI to respect human dignity and truly serve the common good, responsibility must
be clearly defined at every stage: from those who design and develop these systems
to those who use them and rely on them for concrete decisions. In many cases,
Calling for prudence, rigorous evaluation and even, at times, a slower pace in
adopting AI does not mean opposing progress; instead, it is an exercise of
responsible care for the human family. This need is all the more urgent given the
We cannot be satisfied with merely calling for the moralization of machines — the
so-called “alignment” of AI with human values — without also having the courage to
insist on a further condition: the possibility of openly discussing the ethical
In fact, as with every major technological shift, AI tends to amplify the power of
those who already possess economic resources, expertise and access to data. In light
of the common good and the universal destination of goods, this raises serious Cf.
The principles of Social Doctrine offer a framework for understanding this new
reality. In a world where data, computational resources and regulatory influence
remain in the hands of a few, to speak of the common good means exposing this new
Finally, I would like to employ the expression “to disarm,” which is close to my
heart. Disarming AI means freeing it from the mentality of “armed” competition,
which today is not limited simply to the military context, but is also an economic
I wish to address a special appeal to those who develop artificial intelligence. In
one sense, technological innovation can represent human participation in the divine
act of creation. Developers, therefore, bear a particular ethical and spiritual 41
What must not be lost
Having considered the issues of responsibility and governance of AI, we must now
return to our central question: what does it mean to safeguard our humanity? The
risk extends beyond the misuse of certain technologies. More gravely, the pervasive
In reality, elevating any single dimension of human existence to an absolute is
always a mistake. Indeed, disorder does not arise only from scarcity; even unchecked
growth can give rise to impoverishment. In an ecosystem, balance is disrupted when
The quality of a civilization is measured not by the power of its means, but by the
care it is able to offer, by its ability to recognize the other as a face not merely
as a function. The ability to care for one another is a fundamental dimension of our
Underlying narratives: transhumanism and posthumanism
In an attempt to shed light on the cultural assumptions accompanying the ongoing
digital revolution, I would now like to turn our attention to certain currents of
thought that interpret progress as surpassing the human condition, and which are
Transhumanism and posthumanism encompass a range of currents and sensibilities,
making it difficult to define them in a single, unambiguous way. They can be likened
to an archipelago of conceptual “islands,” distinct yet connected by a common “sea”
From the perspective of the Church’s Social Doctrine, the key issue is not the use
of technology as such, but the vision that underlies it. If the human being is
treated as something to be perfected or surpassed, it becomes easier to accept that
The limit, the heart, the grandeur of the human person
Our relationship with life seems to be in crisis today. Everything that appears as a
“limit” — incapacity, illness, old age, suffering, vulnerability — tends to be seen
primarily as a defect to be corrected, rather than as a reality through which our
It is precisely within our limitations that the following find a place: compassion,
as well as a sincere concern for the needs of others; a generosity that can emerge
even in the midst of darkness and failure; spiritual experience and the worship of
Even when limitations are experienced as inner suffering, human wisdom teaches us
not to deny or suppress it, but to integrate it. To eliminate suffering entirely
would mean, in the end, extinguishing love and desire as well. Those who love and
The moral corruption of our limitations as created beings — namely the evil that
clearly agitates the human heart — ruins society and life, at times reaching extreme
forms of inhumanity. Yet even these painful expressions of our limitations leave
Finitude, when truly accepted, does not diminish us but opens us to recognizing the
face of God and others. Indeed, precisely because we experience limits —
vulnerability, suffering and failure — we can recognize the inviolable dignity of
History does not appear solely as a record of human violence, but also as evidence
that humanity is capable of creating institutions that protect our shared life. Over
the past two centuries, this can be seen in several emblematic achievements: the
Certain events make it clear that history can also change when individuals truly
take the dignity of everyone seriously: the civil rights movement in the United
States of America, closely associated with the testimony of Martin Luther King Jr.,
Alongside these public signs, there is a more hidden but decisive story. We see it
in religious communities that choose to serve in poor and dangerous places. We also
see it in the martyrs of fraternity and justice, such as Saint Maximilian Mary
It is this intertwining of just institutions, credible witnesses and daily fidelity
that sustains hope and provides clear direction for technological progress without
allowing the heart to regress. For this reason, humanity — in all its grandeur and
The authentic “more than human”: grace and Christian humanism
The expression “more than human” is not an exclusive domain of technological
promise. For centuries, the Christian tradition has maintained that human beings are
not confined by the boundaries of their own nature; rather, they are called to
When we embrace the possibility of transcending ourselves through God’s grace, we do
not deny our nature, nor do we become less human. On the contrary, as Pope Francis
explained, “We become fully human when we become more than human, when we let God
Two cities and two loves
Christian humanism does not reject science or technology, but embraces them with
gratitude and realism, and grounds them within a higher vocation. The creative
intelligence of humanity is a gift that can alleviate suffering and open up new
Questioning this alternative path of progress and how we interpret and live it is
ultimately a matter of examining our own hearts. The way we understand and shape
relationships, work and institutions, in practice reveals our fundamental values. In
Safeguarding Humanity at a Time of Transformation — Truth, Work, Freedom
Having outlined the context in which the challenge of technological transformation
is situated, especially those linked to AI and to transhumanist and posthumanist
currents, we cannot remain at the level of general analysis alone. When languages
Truth as a common good
Truth and democracy
The use of digital platforms and AI systems is driving profound changes in public
and political communication. Tools that could foster dialogue and participation are
often used to construct distorted narratives and blur the boundaries between truth
Those who command powerful technological and economic resources, along with
substantial human capital for intervention, possess significant capabilities for
influencing cultural change. Ultimately, they can influence a significant number of
The search for truth is an essential element of democracy, which is itself a means
of contributing to the common good. When questions about what is true lose their
appeal, and a pragmatism takes hold that is content with what appears useful or
Communication and the collective imagination
In view of this, it is important to recall that communication “is not only the
transmission of information, but it is also the creation of a culture.” The content
that circulates within digital environments shapes how people perceive the world and
For this reason, those who control digital platforms and means of communication have
a considerable ability to affect the collective imagination and to present a
particular vision of reality as desirable. Such power should be constantly guided by
Toward an ecology of communication
Our first task is neither to demonize nor idolize technological tools, but to
utilize them on the basis of a fundamental principle, namely that truth is a common
good and not the property of those with power or influence. We must therefore
Christian communities, too, are called to commit themselves to transparency in
communication and to the honest pursuit of facts. Sadly, this has not always been
the case. We have witnessed with shame the emergence of painful truths concerning
An educational alliance for the digital age
In an era when truth is often distorted in order to serve particular interests and
communication strategies, the field of education assumes decisive importance. Yet
rapid technological transformations reveal just how unprepared we are on the
Education, by contrast, is a long journey requiring patience, and therefore needs
time for development and for engagement with reality beyond appearances. This is a
fundamental issue because every technology shapes those who use it. Educating people
In recent years, psychological and psychiatric literature has documented with
growing insistence how early and unsupervised exposure to digital devices and social
media can negatively impact sleep, attention span, control of emotions and
It is difficult for parents by themselves to resist the influence of business models
that monetize attention and time. Therefore, it is essential to form an alliance
among policy-makers, educational institutions and families that is capable of
The central role of schools
School is the place where new generations can learn to seek and love the truth, to
reflect on the meaning of life and to recognize the dignity of every person. For
this reason, many parents, who want their children to grow in the capacity to form
The first challenge is socio-political. Both within individual nations and across
different regions of the world, significant inequalities persist concerning access
to basic education and higher studies. In many nations, Governments have not yet
The second major challenge is pedagogical. Many educational systems struggle to keep
pace with change and to support the integral development of students. The advance of
information technologies and AI is rapidly rendering curricula obsolete that were
The third major challenge is intellectual and concerns knowledge. Without careful
attention, an educational system lacking in a love for truth may emerge, in which an
incessant flow of information replaces the essential exercise of research,
72 yet not everyone is willing to practice justice… But perform the works of
justice, keeping in mind that justice and peace have embraced; they are not at odds
with one another. Why do you set yourself against justice? Here, for example, is
The dignity of work at a time of digital transition
The value of work
Since the emergence of her Social Doctrine, beginning with Rerum Novarum, the Church
has emphasized the protection of workers and the need to combat all forms of
exploitation. Above all, however, the Magisterium has recognized in work “the
For these reasons, work is not simply an instrument; it expresses and enhances the
dignity of our lives. It is a requirement of the human condition, a normal path
toward maturity, development and personal fulfilment. In this regard, financial
Today, the convergence of automation, robotics and AI is rapidly transforming the
very structure of work. It is said that this will bring great improvements for
everyone. In reality, however, the “new ways” of working are not necessarily better,
The problem of unemployment
Saint John Paul II recognized that unemployment is a grave evil. Indeed, when it
reaches massive proportions, it becomes a true social calamity that especially
requires the State to exercise responsibility. Today, amid the “fourth industrial
It is certainly desirable for technology to relieve humans of arduous, repetitive or
dangerous tasks and to provide intelligent support for human activity. Yet, the
protection of employment opportunities and the irreplaceable role of the individual
At the same time, we must acknowledge that every real transition involves
discontinuities, for it is uneven, fragmented and sometimes conflictual.
Consequently, no single model of change or universal solution exists, since there
Work remains a fundamental dimension of the human experience, for not only is it a
means of sustenance, but it is also a context for expression, relationships and
contributing to the community. Therefore, the problems related to work extend beyond
In light of this conviction, we can better appreciate the history of the Church’s
Social Doctrine after Rerum Novarum. The initiatives which emerged from that 54
tradition, including associations, trade unions, cooperatives and welfare
At this time of transition, it is not enough to react only when jobs disappear; we
must oversee the transformation in advance. One viable path is, first of all, to
establish social criteria for innovation. Here, every introduction of automation and
An economy that values dignity
The labor market is one area in which the risks associated with new technologies
more clearly emerge. It is thus necessary to remember that economic freedom is not
absolute; it must always be measured against the common good and the dignity of
With prophetic spirit, Pope Francis warned against an economic freedom proclaimed in
words alone, while actual conditions prevent many from benefiting from it. Economic
models that exalt efficiency and individual success often view investment in
It is important to move beyond the current metrics of development — which for more
than eighty years have been tied to the concept of Gross Domestic Product (GDP) —
since these metrics almost systematically neglect aspects essential to the overall
In recent years, finance has increased in importance and has undergone significant
innovation, driven partly by the introduction of cryptocurrencies. The reflections
and observations contained in the teaching of my predecessors, particularly in their
This perspective needs to become part of a broader view of global dynamics. While
the world’s wealth has grown in absolute terms, it is increasingly concentrated in
fewer hands, widening inequalities both within and between countries. “There are a
Just laws and methods of redistribution are certainly necessary for correcting
imbalances, including tax systems that lighten the burden on the weakest and ask for
more from those with greater resources. However, the pursuit of social justice
More than ever, in the age of AI and robotics, it is no longer possible to rely
solely on the “invisible hand” of the market. Politics has the task of orientating
economies and technologies to the common good, promoting dignified work, social
In practical terms, in the age of AI and robotics, ensuring that the economy favors
human dignity means adopting certain criteria for firm action. First, transparency
and accountability: when data and algorithms influence credit distribution,
Families and young people: the social conditions for hope
The family is a primary social good. Founded on the enduring union between a man and
a woman, it is the first environment in which all persons develop their potential,
become aware of their dignity and learn the earliest forms of truth and 1105-1106.
The family, however, is a fragile social good immediately affected by the economic
and technological transformations reshaping the nature of work. It thus requires
cultural, juridical and economic support. The devastating impact of unemployment and
For young people, job insecurity is particularly devastating. As the Bishops of the
United States of America have recalled, work is not merely a source of income but a
crucial sphere in which identity is formed, friendships and relationships are
This gives rise to a specific public responsibility. The State has the duty to
support business activity by fostering conditions favorable to employment, promoting
work where it is lacking and defending it in times of crisis, since it is a primary
Supporting families and young people in this transition requires choices that make
stability feasible. As has been noted above, labor policies need to promote
continuity and the quality of employment, countering insecurity as a normal
Protecting freedom against dependencies and commercialization
Dependencies and societal control
Having reflected on truth and education, work and families, we must now consider the
impact of the digital revolution on human freedom, addressing risks to both the
mental health of individuals and broader social challenges. The subtler forms of
A further risk, less visible but no less serious, is that of social control made
possible by the massive collection of data and use of algorithmic systems. When
every action — movements, purchases, relationships and preferences — leaves a trace,
At the root of these problems lies a technocratic and post-humanist mentality that
tends to regard the human person as an object to be manipulated or a resource to be
optimized,172 removing all safeguards against the unchecked pursuit of profit. What
Breaking the chains of new forms of slavery
This distorted view of the human person is reflected today in various forms of
servitude directly linked to the digital economy. Nothing in the world of AI is
immaterial or magical. Every seemingly immediate and flawless response is the result
The fight against new forms of slavery is a decisive test for the ethical
discernment of AI and digital transformation. In continuity with the tradition
inaugurated by Leo XIII, the Church renews her firm condemnation of all forms of
Human trafficking must be recognized as a contemporary form of slavery and a grave
violation of human dignity. Failing to respond firmly, or tolerating these 60
practices in any way, is in some way to become complicit in today’s sins, which are
In the development of her doctrine, the Church has gradually come to a deeper
awareness of the gravity of these issues. It is true that past events cannot be
judged anachronistically, as though the moral criteria that matured over time had
This is why the memory of past complicity and blindness in the face of the injustice
of slavery becomes a call to vigilance. What we have learned must be translated into
discernment and responsibility in the present. If we want to avoid the need to ask
Even today, colonialism assumes new forms. It no longer dominates only bodies, but
appropriates data, transforming personal lives into exploitable information. Entire
regions, especially those marked by structural fragility and of the Past, Vatican
New forms of slavery are fueled by economic chains and digital infrastructures.
Therefore, action is required on several fronts. First, the supply chains that
underpin the technological industry and the digital economy need to become more
A shared responsibility
The various areas just considered — the search for the truth in public life,
education in the digital environment, the transformation of work, the fragility of
families and new forms of slavery — are not isolated phenomena. Rather, they reflect
From this perspective, the Social Doctrine of the Church calls for a shared
responsibility. It asks that these processes be guided with foresight: by
institutions capable of regulating without stifling, and protecting without taking
The Culture of Power and the Civilization of Love
Having considered how AI is transforming certain aspects of life and society, in
particular the serious implications for human dignity, we must now turn our
attention to the yet more tragic issue of war. Here the question is not merely the
The digital revolution is changing the nature of conflict. Alongside conventional
warfare, there are hybrid forms such as cyberattacks, information manipulation,
campaigns of influence and the automation of strategic decisions. AI acts as an
In this chapter, therefore, I will compare two opposing approaches, which I have
already evoked through biblical imagery in the Introduction. On the one hand, there
is the temptation of constructing the Tower of Babel, relying on power and pride. On
If we examine global dynamics, we can recognize more clearly the spread of a culture
of power characterized by polarization and violence. The modern Babel can be seen
not only in the globalized technocratic paradigm, but also in the remote clash
The civilization of love in the digital age
When Saint Paul VI coined the phrase “the civilization of love,” the world was in
the midst of the Cold War, an arms race and severe economic instability. In that
context, the Church proposed an alternative path to that of ideological opposition
This insight proves even more fundamental in the current context of digital
transformation. Digital networks, the globalized economy and the development of AI
create increasingly tighter bonds, linking — in real time — decisions made in one
The culture of power
In our time, a culture of power is taking hold, in which the availability of
resources and the ability to dominate tend to dictate the agenda and criteria for
decision-making. In this way, the common good of humanity is relegated to the
The normalization of war
In 1965, the words of Saint Paul VI resounded powerfully at the UN General Assembly:
“Never again war, never again war!” We must acknowledge that, despite the desires
and declarations for peace, the past sixty years have been marked by conflicts of
Today, however, we are witnessing a real paradigm shift in public discourse and in
decisions regarding rearmament, with a troubling revival of war as an instrument of
international politics, while the very ethical principles that had previously
We are also witnessing a disconcerting loss of historical memory, as firsthand
accounts of the Holocaust and the two World Wars are disappearing. This leads to a
selective or distorted rewriting of the past, in a context where fake news and the
To all of this, the media and digital dimensions are adding new and decisive
elements. Communication networks, fragmented information environments and algorithms
that reward conflict can magnify polarization and resentment, increase propaganda
Force without limits
The growth of the military-industrial complex has become a defining feature of the
current political landscape and has become a key sector in the economy of various
countries. The close link between economic interests, the military apparatus and
Military arsenals are receiving renewed attention. In the past, recognition of the
threat posed by weapons capable of destroying all of humanity had promoted paths
toward détente and disarmament negotiations. Unfortunately, this approach has been
The same logic applies to conventional warfare. Military force, weak diplomatic
initiatives and the complexity of the interests at stake contribute to conflicts
that tend to become protracted, with extremely high human and environmental costs.
The situation is further destabilized by the presence of new armed operatives, such
as jihadist groups, private militias and criminal networks that mark the end of the
State’s monopoly on the use of force. Often these groups intertwine vague
Weapons and artificial intelligence
The above-mentioned scenario is linked to the unceasing development of weapons
systems, particularly those involving AI. The Holy See has recently observed that
the growing ease with which autonomous weapons systems can be deployed makes war
Sometimes there is talk of “artificial moral agents,” as if machines were able to
distinguish between right and wrong with greater consistency than a human being. Yet
moral judgment cannot be reduced to calculation, for it involves conscience,
It is not enough to invoke a generic type of ethics. Concrete criteria for
discernment must be established. The first such criterion concerns personal
responsibility. When a decision to strike becomes automated or opaque, the risk of
These criteria give rise to certain non-negotiable requirements. First, all systems
used in a war setting must guarantee the possibility of retracing and Antiqua et
Nova (14 January 2025), 99: AAS 117 (2025), 202-203. 68 reconstructing
The crisis of multilateralism
The culture of power also stems from the crisis of the multilateral system. The
institutions established to safeguard the concept of a common future for all peoples
and a global common good appear to have been weakened. This is due not only to
What has also re-emerged is the temptation to forge a collective identity in
opposition to an enemy, fueled by narratives in which each party portrays itself as
a victim entitled to retribution. The reduction of complex issues into simplistic
In this context, peacebuilding has been relegated to a secondary role. Cooperation
for development, disarmament, conflict prevention and the establishment of mutual
trust are neglected in the name of power politics. The achievements of humanitarian
A supposed political realism
We live at a time of significant spiritual and cultural blindness. A false
pragmatism urges us to sever the roots of our history, as if it were possible to
inaugurate a kind of “new creation” detached from the past. Even those who cite
At the core of these issues is a false realism, based not only on the prevailing
mentality of force, but on the cultural and anthropological belief that war is an
inevitable part of human nature. It is said that things have always been this way,
In such a climate, nihilism and pragmatism become intertwined and end up normalizing
grave errors. Religious extremism and identity-based fanaticism ally themselves with
irrational economic policies, while politics often turns to misinformation and
This, then, is the fertile ground for new wars that are perhaps even more dangerous
than those of the past, since they tend to disregard all ethical limits. What was
once considered unacceptable can now be carried out almost without hesitation, while
In these situations, the issue of concrete safeguards to prevent future violence
remains an open question. When a culture normalizes and justifies conflict, a
dangerous pathway opens up, in that what seems unthinkable today 70 may become
A particular responsibility rests on the shoulders of those who work in the field of
research. All the key players in this field — scientists, business owners,
investors, academic authorities, politicians and others — must work with a
Building the civilization of love
The construction of a world in a state of perpetual conflict is an evil and must be
named for what it is. This way of portraying our current situation may seem bleak or
pessimistic, yet I consider it necessary to do so. The Christian perspective,
A closer analysis of history confirms this. Even in the darkest nights, the Lord
raises up men and women who refuse to give up, who persevere in doing good, who
protect the vulnerable and open pathways to reconciliation. The memory of the
We can all do our part
At this point, however, a subtle temptation may emerge, namely the thought that the
problems are too big and we are too small, and that our choices, therefore, cannot
make a difference. This is a polite form of resignation, often disguised as realism.
The twentieth-century Catholic author J.R.R. Tolkien, in the words of a protagonist
in one of his novel’s, described our responsibility in this way: “It is not our part
to master all the tides of the world, but to do what is in us for the succour of
The need to disarm words
The first contribution we can make toward a more humane civilization is to be
mindful of our words. “Let us disarm words and we will help to disarm the world.”
Words have enormous power, something we experience in our daily interactions; for
Building peace through justice
All of us, at every level, can contribute to building the foundation of peace, which
is justice. We do not merely seek any kind of peace — such as an absence of conflict
at any cost — but instead, the true peace born of justice. “There exists a very
Adopting the perspective of victims
There are times when, in order to remain human, we must set aside our reservations
and take a stand. In some conflicts, it is unjust to remain neutral, nor is it
enough merely to claim that we are not complicit. When we witness the bombing of
Giving space to the perspectives and voices of victims through communication and
education helps us to become aware of the abyss of evil inherent in war, and
generally in all forms of violence. It helps us to reject the normalization of
Cultivating a healthy realism
We are in need of a healthy realism that avoids both political idealism and
cynicism. There is a kind of idealism that, in order to preserve its own worldview,
tends to choose facts selectively, distorting and renaming them. Its proponents
Reviving dialogue
In order to build the civilization of love, we must engage in dialogue, for this is
the primary means of coexistence between people and nations, and it is the
alternative to open conflict. On the eve of the Second World War, Pius XII affirmed
Indeed, dialogue is an ordinary part of human life and does not only concern
relations between States. It involves acquiring an attitude that seeks to forge
bonds of fraternity built on listening, an open demeanor, making time for each other
At the political level, there is an urgent need to shift from the “culture of power”
to a genuine “culture of negotiation,” in which dialogue and diplomacy become the
standard means of resolving conflicts. Giorgio La Pira expressed the hope that “the
To those who have the honor and responsibility of governing, I would like to repeat
the words that I spoke at the start of my Pontificate: “The peoples of our world
desire peace, and to their leaders I appeal with all my heart: Let us meet, let us
In rejecting the mindset of violence, interreligious dialogue plays a decisive role,
because at the heart of the great spiritual paths lies a message of peace. Whereas
those who use the name of God to legitimize terrorism, violence or war betray his
The necessity of diplomacy and multilateralism
In international relations, dialogue is an irreplaceable diplomatic tool for
preventing conflicts and rebuilding bonds of trust. Faced with the impulsive
broadcasts, aggressive rhetoric and power politics that characterize our time, “the
Cyberspace too has become a battleground. Cyberattacks, data manipulation and
campaigns of influence, orchestrated with the help of AI, can destabilize entire
countries even before open armed conflict erupts. Moreover, in this area, the
International organizations, particularly the United Nations, are essential
instruments for promoting a civilization of love, for they can foster dialogue among
nations and promote the peaceful resolution of conflicts, the integral development
In the international context, the Holy See’s diplomacy adopts the Gospel’s principle
of mercy as a concrete criterion for political action. This is one of the ways in
which the Holy See places itself at the service of humanity, thereby appealing to
Praying and hoping
These avenues for exercising responsibility are sustained by prayer, and in turn
nourish prayer. Indeed, for each of us, peace primarily comes “from God, God who
loves us all, unconditionally.” It is a gift given by Jesus to his disciples on the
Conclusion
“Let each builder choose with care how to build” (1 Cor 3:10). With these words,
Saint Paul encouraged the Christians of Corinth to preserve unity. Dear brothers and
sisters, we have reflected on the world we are building, and we asked ourselves what
The Word became flesh
Our world is filled with attempts to seize control of markets and spheres of
influence, often shrouded in reassuring rhetoric and seductive ideologies. Yet our
hearts yearn for an approach that is wise and benevolent, akin to that which Mary
At the heart of everything is the mystery of the Incarnation, the Word who became
flesh and dwelt among us. The flesh of the Son, poor and vulnerable, evokes the
flesh of so many brothers and sisters stripped of their dignity and reduced to
In the promises of transhumanism and some posthumanist currents of thought, which
seek an enhanced and almost disembodied humanity, we recognize a yearning that is of
concern to us, namely the need for a fuller life, less exposed to limitations and
For this reason, as a believer among believers, I invite everyone to contemplate, in
the face of the Son of God, the grandeur of humanity that shines a light also on the
era of AI. In Christ, we are called to cooperate in the work of creation, rather
One body in Christ
The spirituality that we need is a Eucharistic spirituality, that is, a spirituality
of ecclesial unity in love. The Incarnation and the Paschal Mystery reveal God
entering into our human condition and transforming it through the gift of himself.
The “Amen” that we say in the liturgy, the Body we eat and the Blood we drink shape
our entire lives. The Eucharist “is an extremely personal encounter with the Lord
and yet never simply an act of individual piety.” In the Eucharist we find a visible
The construction site of our time
The spirituality I wish to commend is that of the “wise architect” who, driven by
hope for the Kingdom of God, is committed to building the world for the common good
(cf. 1 Cor 3:10). As I mentioned at the beginning of this reflection,217 the task of
Let us remain faithful to the truth! Living amid incessant flows of information,
opinions and images, we know how easy it can be to influence decisions and
preferences through increasingly sophisticated algorithms. In this context, it is
Let us invest in education, beginning with ourselves! We all need to learn how to
engage with the digital world in a human way, as an integral part of our education
in the faith and in a life lived according to the Gospel. Indeed, we must consider
Let us cultivate relationships! In an era that favors speed and fragmentation, the
human person still yearns to receive care and recognition from attentive minds, kind
words and hands capable of tenderness. The digital culture multiplies connections
Let us love justice and peace! The same technologies that facilitate communication
and access to resources can also support models that exploit the Intelligence” (13
November 2025): L’Osservatore Romano, 13 November 2025, 3. 80 most vulnerable,
As we look to the future, I would like to recall the image of Nehemiah whom we chose
as our companion and guide at the outset. Nehemiah heard the cry of a devastated
city, brought that pain to prayer, discerned before God, asked for help, received
The image of rebuilding Jerusalem evokes the New Testament promise of the holy city,
which is given to us first and foremost as a gift. In the Book of Revelation, the
new Jerusalem descends as a gift for all God’s people, “prepared as a bride adorned
The song of hope: the Magnificat
After having considered faith, which contemplates the Father’s loving plan; love,
which unites us in one ecclesial body; and hope, which sustains our actions in the
world, the fourth pillar of this program for Christian life is prayer. Mary’s 2026,
The Blessed Virgin Mary not only teaches us to recognize God’s invisible work, but
also directs our gaze to “the points at which humanity is broken and the world
becomes distorted: the contrast between the humble and the powerful, the poor and
With the same faith as Mary, let us become “weavers of hope” in our world, sharing
who we are and what we have, so that the presence of Jesus may grow among us and his
Kingdom take shape. In the humble fidelity of daily life, even the era of AI can